Finding aid for the Nathan Pritikin papers LSC.1628
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Pritikin Research Foundation/Longevity Research Institute: Minutes, Other Records
  - Longevity Research Institute/Pritikin Research Foundation: By-laws, Name Change, Foundation Tax Status. (Box 36)
  - Longevity Research Institute Documents. (Box 36)
  - Longevity Research Institute: Advisory Board Minutes (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation/Longevity Research Institute: Board of Trustees/Directors Lists. (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation/Longevity Research Institute: Board of Advisors Lists. (Box 36)
  - Invitations to join Advisory Board. (Box 36)
  - Longevity Research Institute/Pritikin Research Foundation: Stationery (evolution). (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation: Dr. James Barnard, Director
    - Curriculum vitae; statements on Pritikin Program. (Box 36)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence. (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation: Wilma Keller, Director of Development; Penelope Grenoble (Executive Director)
    - Wilma Keller. (Box 36)
    - Penelope Grenoble. (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation: Robinson, Miles H., M.D.
    (See also Boxes 7, 8, 9, 17)
    - Biography, Curriculum vitae. (Box 36)
    - Correspondence with Pritikin and staff. (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation: Fund-Raising Efforts
    - [No further description available]. (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation: 1. Library; 2. Proposed Journal
    - Beginnings of Library. (Box 36)
    - Library (Box 36)
      (See also Box no.1, "Memorials")
    - Pritikin Research Foundation Journal (proposed). (Box 36)
  - Pritikin Research Foundation Newsletter
    - PRF: Newsletter articles. (Box 36)
    - PRF: Newsletters. (Box 36)
- Lectures, References
  - Educational material for Pritikin lectures: Handout sheets
    - Lecture hand-outs for early lectures. (Box 37)
    - Lecture hand-outs planned to be used with post-8/84 lectures. (Box 37)
  - Lecture Revisions (latest transcripts), 1984
    (See accompanying audio cassettes)
    - Lecture no.1: Nutrition. (Box 37)
    - Slides for Lecture no.1: Nutrition. (Box 37)
    - Lecture no.2: Digestion and excesses. (Box 37)
    - Slides for Lecture no.2: Digestion and excesses. (Box 37)
    - Lecture no.3: Heart disease. (Box 37)
    - Slides for Lecture no.3: Heart disease. (Box 37)
    - Lecture no.4: Hypertension. (Box 37)
    - Slides for Lecture no.4: Hypertension. (Box 37)
    - Lecture no.5: Diabetes. (Box 37)
    - Slides for Lecture no.5: Diabetes. (Box 37)
    - Lecture no.6: Lipotoxemia: Poisoning from excess fat and cholesterol. (Box 37)
    - Slides for Lecture no.6: Lipotoxemia. (Box 37)
  - Early Lecture Series Transcripts: Composition of Foods (Lecture no.1).
    - [No further description available]. (Box 37)
  - E.L.S.T.
    - Digestion and excesses (Lecture no.2). (Box 37)
    - Cardiovascular disease: genesis/epidemiology (Lecture no.3). (Box 37)
    - Prevention of cardiovascular disease in the U.S. (Lecture no.4). (Box 37)
    - Medical intervention in cardiovascular disease (Lecture no.5). (Box 37)
    - Angina and hypertension (Lecture no.6). (Box 37)
    - Exercise (Lecture no.7). (Box 37)
    - Cancer, a preventable disease (Lecture no.8). (Box 37)
    - Cancer II (Lecture no.9). (Box 37)
    - Diabetes I (Lecture no.10). (Box 37)
    - Diabetes II (Lecture no.11). (Box 37)
    - Sight (Lecture no.12). (Box 37)
    - Arthritis (Lecture no.13). (Box 37)
    - Hearing Loss/Gallstones (Lecture no.14). (Box 37)
    - Recommendations (Lecture no.15). (Box 37)
  - Early Lecture Series: Original Notes and Papers
    - Lecture outlines. (Box 37)
    - Composition of foods lecture. (Box 37)
    - Cancer lectures, I and II lectures. (Box 37)
    - Cardiovascular diseases, I, lecture. (Box 37)
    - Hypertension lecture. (Box 37)
    - Diabetes lecture. (Box 37)
    - Sight lecture. (Box 37)
    - Gout lecture. (Box 37)
    - Summary lecture. (Box 37)
  - Lecture: Heart ()., Probably Late 1970s
    - [No further description available]. (Box 37)
  - Lecture Revisions: References, 1984
    - [No further description available]. (Box 37)
  - Nutrition I: Composition of Foods
    - [No further description available]. (Box 38)
    - Slides only. (Box 38)
    - References only: A - L. (Box 38)
    - References only: M - S. (Box 38)
    - References only: T - Z. (Box 38)
  - Nutrition II: Digestion and Excesses
    - (August 1979). (Box 38)
    - Slides and hand-outs. (Box 38)
    - References only: A - G. (Box 38)
    - References only: H - L. (Box 38)
    - References only: M - Z. (Box 38)
  - Beverages, Health Foods and Smoking
    - Beverages and smoking: Original lecture. (Box 38)
    - Beverages and smoking: References only. (Box 38)
    - Health Foods: Original lecture. (Box 38)
    - Health Foods: References only. (Box 38)
  - no.3: Cardiovascular I
    - Genesis and epidemiology. (Box 38)
    - References only (two files). (Box 38)
  - no.4: Cardiovascular II
    - Lecture. (Box 38)
    - References only. (Box 38)
  - no.5: Cardiovascular III
    - Lecture. (Box 38)
    - References only. (Box 38)
  - no.6: Angina and Hypertension
    - Lecture. (Box 38)
    - Slides only. (Box 38)
    - References only. (Box 38)
  - no.7: Exercise
    - Lecture. (Box 38)
    - References only. (Box 38)
  - no.8: Cancer I
    - Lecture. (Box 39)
    - References only, no.1-22. (Box 39)
    - References only, no.24-43. (Box 39)
    - References only, no.44-61. (Box 39)
  - no.9: Cancer II
    - Lecture. (Box 39)
    - References only. (Box 39)
  - no.10: Diabetes I
    - Lecture (and slides). (Box 39)
    - References only. (Box 39)
  - no.11: Diabetes II
    - Lecture. (Box 39)
    - References only (2 files). (Box 39)
  - no.12: Sight
    - Lecture. (Box 39)
    - References only. (Box 39)
    - References and slides. (Box 39)
  - no.13: Arthritis
    - Lecture. (Box 39)
    - References only. (Box 39)
  - no.14: Hearing Loss and Gallstones
    - Original lecture. (Box 39)
    - References only. (Box 39)
  - no.15: Recommendations
    - Summary Lecture. (Box 39)
    - Lecture (Original). (Box 39)
    - Lecture: References only: A - C. (Box 39)
    - Lecture: References only: D - Z. (Box 39)
  - Lectures: Slide Production and Use
    - Slide production. (Box 39)
    - Lecture slide checkout. (Box 39)
    - Revised slide sequence - Nathan's notes. (Box 39)
  - Educational Material for Pritikin Programs: Films
    - Swank film. (Box 39)
    - Eula Weaver film. (Box 39)
- Copies of Artwork - Lectures
  - Composition of foods. (Box 40)
  - Digestion and excesses. (Box 40)
  - Cardiovascular I. (Box 40)
  - Cardiovascular II. (Box 40)
  - Cardiovascular III. (Box 40)
  - Angina and hypertension. (Box 40)
  - Exercise. (Box 40)
  - Cancer I. (Box 40)
  - Cancer II. (Box 40)
  - Diabetes I. (Box 40)
  - Diabetes II. (Box 40)
  - Sight. (Box 40)
  - Arthritis. (Box 40)
  - Hearing and Gallstones. (Box 40)
  - Recommendations. (Box 40)
- Original Artwork for Slides for Lectures
  - no.1 Nutrition. (Box 41)
  - no.2 Digestion and Excesses. (Box 41)
  - no.3 Heart Disease. (Box 41)
  - no.4 Hypertension. (Box 41)
  - no.5 Diabetes. (Box 42)
  - no.6 Lipotoxemia. (Box 42)
- Slides for Lectures
  - Miscellaneous Slides for Lectures. (Box 43)
  - Lectures I-VII. (Box 44)
  - Lectures VIII-XV and 900-Patient Study. (Box 45)
  - Prevention Lectures One to Nine. (Box 46)
  - Prevention Lectures Ten and Eleven and Slide Catalogues. (Box 47)
  - Pritikin Better Health Program Slides. (Box 48)
- Audio Cassettes
  - Longevity Research Institute (LRI)/Pritikin Research Foundation (PRF)
    - [No further description available]. (Box 49)
  - Annual Educational Conferences; Longevity Research Institute, (1977-1984)
    - [No further description available]. (Box 49)
  - Annual Advisory Board Meetings, (1977-78)
    - LRI First Annual Educational Conference () - Tape no.1-10, 10 tapes., January 1977 (Box 49)
    - LRI Advisory Board Meetings () - Tape no.11-12, 2 tapes., January 16, 1977 and January 21, 1978 (Box 49)
    - LRI Second Annual Educational Conference (), "Diet and Exercise in the Treatment of Degenerative Disease" - Tape no.13-24, 12 tapes., January 1978 (Box 49)
    - LRI Third Annual Educational Conference; PRF Fourth Annual Educational Conference - Tape no.25-40, 16 tapes., (1979) (1980) (Box 49)
    - PRF Fifth Annual Educational Conference, "Management of Cardiovascular Disease and obesity through Diet and Exercise" - Tape no.41-50, 10 tapes., (1981) (Box 49)
    - PRF Conference, co-sponsored by Mt. Sinai School of Medicine, "The Medical Benefits of Risk Reduction Through Nutritional and Lifestyle Changes" - Tape no.51-56, 6 tapes., 1984 (Box 49)
  - Biographical: History of Pritikin's Nutritional Career
    - Tape no.57-58. 2 tapes. (Box 49)
  - Pritikin Lectures to Program Participants
    - Lectures on nutrition and various degenerative diseases - Tape no.59-83, 25 tapes. (Box 49)
    - Pritikin Longevity Center educational lectures - Tape no.84-89, 6 tapes., 1980 (Box 49)
    - Lecture Series (probably ) - Tape no.90-95, 6 tapes., 1982-1984 (Box 49)
      1. Nutrition.
      2. Digestion and excesses.
      3. Heart disease.
      4. Hypertension.
      5. Diabetes.
      6. Lipotoxemia.
    - Latest lecture revisions - Tape no.96-101, 6 tapes., (1984) (Box 49)
    - Pritikin Better Health Program, Denise Vilven training sessions I-III - Tape no.102-104, 3 tapes., (1981) (Box 49)
  - Case Histories, Interviews and Testimonials
    - Long Beach Study patient interviews - Tape no.105-108, 4 tapes. (Box 49)
    - Pritikin Program case histories and testimonials - Tape no.109-114, 6 tapes. (Box 49)
    - Author Pat McGrady's interviews with Nathan Pritikin and Longevity Center physicians in connection with writing of "Pritikin Program for Diet and Exercise" - Tape no.115-116, 2 tapes (defective tape). (Box 49)
  - Miscellaneous Tapes
    - Pritikin lecture, "High Carbohydrate Diets: Maligned and Misunderstood" - Tape no.117, 1 tape. (Box 49)
    - Pritikin question-and-answer sessions with participants at Longevity Center - Tape no.118-119, 2 tapes. (Box 49)
    - Pritikin interviews and talks on media - Tape no.120-135, 16 tapes (1 may be defective). (Box 49)
    - AHA Convention, dinner/discussion with cardiologists at Longevity Center (November 15, 1979) - Tape no.136-137, 2 tapes. (Box 49)
    - "Ode to the Longevity Center" by Charles Wood, participant at Longevity Center session no.66 - Tape no.138, 1 tape. (Box 49)
    - 100th session anniversary tape: A message from Nathan Pritikin, Dr. Steven Zifferblatt and Dr. Cleaves Bennett - Tape no.139, 1 tape. (Box 49)
    - Longevity Center graduation programs created by participants - Tape no.140-141, 2 tapes. (Box 49)
    - Song with orchestral background: "Mr. Pritikin Man" by Dean A. Crawford, Tape no.142, 1 tape. (Box 49)
- Photographs/Films
  - Family Relationships; Early Years
    - Family relationships; early years. (Box 50)
    - Biography ("Pritikin; The Man Who Healed America's Heart") photos. (Box 50)
  - Previous Careers
    - Photography (Chicago, Illinois). (Box 50)
    - Glass Products Company (Chicago, Illinois). (Box 50)
    - Glass Products Company (Santa Barbara, California). (Box 50)
  - Home: 627 Lilac Drive, Montecito, California
    - Home Medical Library. (Box 50)
    - Entertaining and working at home. (Box 50)
  - Media Appearances, Book Tours, Speaking Engagements
    - Book tours; book promotion. (Box 50)
    - Australia, book promotion. (Box 50)
    - TV programs. (Box 50)
    - Speaking engagements. (Box 50)
  - Longevity Research Institute/Pritikin Research Foundation Educational Conferences
    - Mt. Sinai/PRF, Educational Conference., 1984 (Box 50)
    - 4th Annual Educational Conference, (1980). (Box 50)
    - 3rd Annual Educational Conference, (1979). (Box 50)
    - 2nd Annual Educational Conference, (1978). (Box 50)
    - 1st Annual Educational Conference, (1977). (Box 50)
  - Pennsylvania Pritikin Center (at Downingtown)
    - Pennsylvania Pritikin Center (at Downingtown). (Box 50)
  - Santa Monica Longevity Center
    - Library dedication (posthumous). (Box 50)
    - Santa Monica Longevity Center. (Box 50)
    - Pritikin with participants. (Box 50)
    - First graduation class, Santa Monica Longevity Center. (Box 50)
    - Non-residential program at Center. (Box 50)
  - Mar Monte Location: Santa Barbara Longevity Center
    - Santa Barbara Longevity Center, Mar Monte Hotel location. (Box 50)
    - Staff and participants. (Box 50)
    - Introduction ceremonies, parties and theatricals. (Box 50)
  - Turnpike Lodge Location: Santa Barbara Longevity Center
    - Santa Barbara Longevity Center: Turnpike Lodge location. (Box 50)
  - Longevity Center session, Santa Barbara (Mar Monte)
    - Session group photos and lists (Mar Monte Hotel). (Box 50)
  - Publicity Shots (Nathan Pritikin)
    - Publication of "Pritikin Program for Diet and Exercise." (Box 50)
    - Running pictures. (Box 50)
    - Desk poses. (Box 50)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Eula Weaver. (Box 50)
    - "Ironman" Triathlon. (Box 50)
    - Honorary Doctorate, Kirksville College of Osteopathic Medicine. (Box 50)
    - Long Beach Study. (Box 50)
    - Pritikin Cruise. (Box 50)
    - "Special" personalities. (Box 50)
  - Films
    - "Today" Show: "New Wrinkles in Aging" ()., March 15, 1977 (Box 50)
    - "60 Minutes." (Box 50)
    - Pritikin on "60 Minutes." (Box 50)
    - "60 Minutes" (2nd program - check-up). (Box 50)
    - Stalking Immortality. (Box 53)
    - Our Three Patients. (Box 53)
    - Scrapbook of media articles immediately following Pritikin's death. (Box 53)
      (Removed from Box 1)
- Videocassettes
  - Interviews, (Large cassettes)
    - Young Again (Robert Stabler Entertainment), no.47-1. (Box 51)
    - Today Show,, no.47-2., March 15, 1987 (Box 51)
    - Lynn Gordon Show,, no.47-3., July 28, 1977 (Box 51)
    - Howard Wise Interview,, no.47-4., August 8, 1977 (Box 51)
    - Michael Jackson Show,, no.47-5., June 25, 1978 (Box 51)
    - Today Show,, no.47-6., October 5, 1981 (Box 51)
  - Interviews, (Small cassettes)
    - Channel 8, Nathan Pritikin, no.47-7. (Box 51)
    - CBS Press Conference: Pritikin, Ellis, Massey,, no.47-8., April 18, 1980 (Box 51)
    - Today Show,, no.47-9., May 29, 1981 (Box 51)
    - Dr. John McDougall, Pritikin Interview:, no.47-10., Late 1982 (Box 51)
    - Dr. John McDougall, Pritikin Interview:, no.47-11., Late 1982 (Box 51)
    - Diane Glazer Interview, no.47-12. (Box 51)
    - James Irwin re Pritikin,, no.47-13., March 1, 1982 (Box 51)
    - Fitness Magazine: Pritikin, Tennile and Seaver Family, no.47-14. (Box 51)
    - 21 Club, Nathan Pritikin,, no.47-15., April 11, 1984 (Box 51)
    - ABC Nightline: TV interviews of Pritikin, Interspersed Segments, no.47-16. (Box 51)
    - ABC & CBS newsclips of LDL reduction study,, no.47-17., 1986 (Box 51)
    - "The Pritikin Choice for the athlete and the average American," no.47-18. (Box 51)
    - Nathan Pritikin speaks from the heart,, no.47-19., November, 1984 (Box 51)
  - The Pritikin Promise
    - Nathan Pritikin Publicity:, no.47-20., October 1983; (Large cassette) (Box 51)
    - Nathan Pritikin Publicity:, no.47-21., October 1983; (Large cassette, copy) (Box 51)
    - Exercise Program, no.47-22. (Box 51)
    - Exercise Program, no.47-23. (Box 51)
    - The Pritikin Promise: New Way Gourmet no.118, no.47-24. (Box 51)
    - The Pritikin Promise: New Way Gourmet no.132, no.47-25. (Box 51)
  - Mt. Sinai Hospital Medical Conference, April 1984
    - Pritikin Dinner Meeting, no.47-26. (Box 51)
    - Mt. Sinai Medical Conference, no.47-27. (Box 51)
    - Mr. Sinai Medical Panel; Home teachers, no.47-28. (Box 51)
- Videocassettes
  - Videocassettes - Santa Monica Center
    - Sunday Orientation - Amy Fates (12-2-84), no.48-1. (Box 52)
    - Introduction to Diet - J. Peters (12-3-84; Making the Most of Nutrition and Exercise - T. Lewis (12-3-84), no.48-2. (Box 52)
    - Health Risk Factors - Playing the Odds - Dr. Diane Hanson (), no.48-3., December 4, 1984 (Box 52)
    - Blood Evaluations - Dr. M. Rosenthal (), no.48-4., December 5, 1984 (Box 52)
    - Composition of Foods - D. Vilven (); Planning Your Diet Strategy - J. Peters (12-5-84), no.48-5., December 5, 1984 (Box 52)
    - Challenge to Today's Medicine - Dr. J. Barnard (); Exercise and Your Heart - Dr. J. Barnard (), no.48-6., November 28, 1984 December 12, 1984 (Box 52)
    - Dining Out - D. Vilven (), no.48-7., December 10, 1984 (Box 52)
    - How Diet Affects Circulation - J. Hall (); High Blood Pressure - J. Hall (December 11, 1984), no.48-8., December 6, 1984 (Box 52)
    - Vitamins and Minerals - D. Vilven (), no.48-9., December 14, 1984 (Box 52)
    - Supermarket Shopping - D. Vilven, no.48-10. (Box 52)
    - Speedy and Spicy (PM) - T. Lewis (), no.48-11., December 17, 1984 (Box 52)
  - Pritikin Kitchen Chemistry - Harriet Roth
    - The Five Principles of Pritikin Cooking; "Soups: Some Like It Hot," no.48-12. (Box 52)
    - Breakfast Preparation; "Soups: Cool and Refreshing," no.48-13. (Box 52)
    - Dairy Day; "The Incredible Crepe," no.48-14. (Box 52)
    - "The Art of Recipe Adaptation; Everything You Always Wanted to Know about Vegetables," no.48-15. (Box 52)
    - Preparing Pritikin for the Week; "Salad Magic," no.48-16. (Box 52)
    - Pasta Party; "Fast Foods a la Pritikin," no.48-17. (Box 52)
    - Buffet Recipes; Hors d'Oeuvres, no.48-18. (Box 52)
  - Educational (Large VCRS)
    - Recommendations: Vitamins and Minerals, no.48-19. (Box 52)
    - Nutritional Relationship to Degenerative Disease, no.48-20. (Box 52)
    - Nutritional Relationship to Degenerative Disease, no.48-21. (Box 52)
    - Excesses of Common Diseases, no.48-22. (Box 52)
    - Sunday Nite Orientation, no.48-23. (Box 52)
  - Miscellaneous Large VCRS
    - Sutton, Class no.24, Dr. R. Murnane, President American Heart Association, no.48-24. (Box 52)
    - Nathan Pritikin: Inserts (Barry & Enright), no.48-25. (Box 52)
    - Eula Weaver - "Live It Up," no.48-26. (Box 52)
  - Educational Small VCRS
    - Food Slides, no.48-27. (Box 52)
    - Food slides and hamster films, no.48-28. (Box 52)
  - Miscellaneous Small VCR
    - Pritikin Follies, Class no.25, 48-29. (Box 52)